Well, all right. It's time to round out
our study of unit 4 and talk about the
nature of southern society from 1800 to
1848. And I just need to tell you that
if your little tum tum gets squeamish
about slavery, well then go chug a
bottle of Pepto-Bismol because there's a
whole lot of it. So, if you're ready to
get them brain cows milk, let's get to
it. Okay, so before we talk about
slavery and its place in southern
society, let me just explain the general
idea of southern identity. And if you
want it in shorthand, southerners
identify themselves as king cotton. And
that encompassed a few related strands.
First of all, ever since the colonial
period, the south was mainly
agricultural and in various eras they
majored in indigo production or tobacco
etc. But during this period, the
southern geography and economy was
dominated by the growth and export of
cotton. And that reality was only
intensified thanks to the widespread
adoption of the cotton gin and the
increasing availability of inexpensive
land due to improved transportation and
the forced removal of American Indians.
And second, remember from earlier videos
that during this period, the US went
through a cataclysmic economic upheaval
known as the market revolution. And
basically that development encouraged
the growth of the national economy while
simultaneously transforming America's
regional economies. And its effect on
regional economies was twofold. And
although they seemed like opposites, the
effects were more like two sides of the
same coin. So on one side of the coin,
the market revolution linked the
regional economies of the north, south,
and west into a tighter interdependent
relationship. But on the other side of
the coin, that kind of integration
encouraged each region to become more
distinct from the others by specializing
in what they were best at producing. So
the whole point is this. As a result of
the market revolution, the South doubled
down on cotton production and leaned
into its distinct identity as the chief
exporter of raw materials for the US and
other international trading partners.
And this fed into their sense of vital
importance to the nation because they
understood that their ability to produce
cotton was a fundamental ingredient of
the growth of the US economy. And with
that, it's time to explore the southern
relationship with slavery. Because
without slavery, king cotton was merely
a common popper. But before we do, since
we're at the end of the unit, let me
just mention that if you need help
getting an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May, then you might want to
check out my A Push Himler review guide.
It's got everything you need to study as
fast as possible for your exam. So, if
that's something that you're into, then
get that clicky finger out and check the
link in the description. Well, all
right, here we go. Let's talk about how
slavery was understood to be a vital
ingredient to the South and their way of
life. Now, if you have the idea in your
mind that every white person in the
South lived on a massive cotton
plantation and own large groups of
enslaved laborers, then smack that idea
right out of your head because that is
not how it was. In fact, we can pretty
neatly divide the southern white
population of this period into four
distinct categories. First, there was a
very small minority of elite wealthy
planters who owned more than 50 enslaved
workers. Second, there was another small
minority of white planters who did not
have the wealth or the sprawling acorage
of the elite planters, but they did
claim ownership over a few enslaved
laborers. And then third was the vast
majority of poorer white farmers known
as yman farmers who worked their own
land and could not afford even a single
enslaved person. And then fourth, you
add the poor whites who own no land and
simply hired themselves out to planters
for seasonal labor whenever they could
find it. So for our purposes, you just
have to remember that only a tiny
percentage of white southern planters
held black people in bondage while a
massive percentage did not. So when I
say slavery was considered a vital
ingredient in the southern way of life,
I reckon you should be growing a
question mark over your head. And maybe
if I put it in modern terms, it might be
easier to understand. So, as of the time
of this recording, there exist in the
United States something like a thousand
billionaires compared to a total
population of about 340 million. Now,
flying on private jets is a vital
ingredient in a billionaire's way of
life because when you're that rich, you
don't really want to mix with the
lowerass cattle that fly on commercial
airlines. Anyway, what if this pitifully
small number of billionaires began to
claim that flying on private jets is the
American way of life? In fact, if you
don't fly on a private jet, then can you
even call yourself an American? I mean,
if they started saying that, I think the
other 339,990,000
of us would be like, "Well, apparently
all that cash didn't buy you any more
brains, cuz that's the dumbest thing I
ever heard." But that's kind of how it
was in the South during this period. A
very small handful of wealthy elites
claimed that slavery was in fact a vital
ingredient to the southern identity,
even though the vast majority of
southern whites could not relate in the
slightest. But over time, those elite
planters were able to convince the rest
of the southern white population that
slavery was what made them who they
were. And a significant reason they were
so keen to convince everyone of this was
because countries in Europe and South
America began abolishing slavery and
states in the north were multiplying
their own abolitionist movements. And to
those southern elites, abolitionism
presented an existential threat both to
their wealth and their social status.
And so they launched efforts to unite
all southern white people against black
Americans. And how in the world did they
pull that off? Well, one strategy was to
tighten the bonds between elite
planters, yman farmers, and poor whites.
And the elites did this by loaning the
money in times of need and transporting
yman farmers goods to markets etc. And
in this way the majority of whites in
the south became at least socially
indebted to the elite. But in many cases
they were financially indebted as well.
And that meant they could not afford to
fall out of favor with these large
planters. Additionally, many yman
farmers clung to the belief that one day
they themselves would grow wealthy
enough to own at least a few enslaved
people. It was kind of like the southern
version of the American dream. But by
far the most successful effort to unite
southern white society was the
perpetuation of new ideologies. And
there are two you need to know. First
was the idea of white supremacy, which
was the belief that the members of the
white race, regardless of wealth,
status, or education, were fundamentally
superior to members of the black race.
And again, this notion was not a given
in southern society before this period.
Like prior to this, it wasn't unusual
for poor whites to work with and be
friendly with poor blacks since they had
a lot in common on account of their
shared socio-economic status. But the
notion of white supremacy shut down that
kind of interaction by creating a racial
division between the two groups. And
that meant that even the poorest of poor
white southerners were at least wealthy
in one respect, namely they had won the
genetic lottery, which is to say they
were not black. But then the second
ideology that united southern whites and
further diminished the status of
enslaved blacks was the changing notion
of the morality of slavery. Now
hopefully you remember from the last
video that slaveolding founders like
Thomas Jefferson and George Washington
and James Madison relied on slavery for
their wealth, but they also believed it
to be a morally repugnant institution
and a fundamental contradiction to the
notion of liberty. But, you know, I
guess that conviction didn't cause them
to lose too much sleep at night because
none of them made any significant
strides to push against the perpetuation
of the institution. I mean, to be fair,
they did seem to believe that as the
United States grew, slavery would just
sort of die out. But, as I've
established in multiple other videos,
that is emphatically not what happened.
Regardless, the point is among elite
slaveholders before this period, slavery
was understood as a necessary evil. They
didn't like it. Some even thought it was
immoral, but they believed that they had
no choice but to perpetuate the
institution, but perpetuate it with a
guilty conscience. During this period,
southern elites put the entire kibash on
that guilty conscience and turned the
whole moral estimation of slavery on its
head. Hereafter, slavery was no longer a
necessary evil, but rather a positive
good. Now, the clearest and most famous
articulation of this position came from
John C. Calhoun, whom you may remember
as Andrew Jackson's vice president and
the architect of the nullification
crisis. And I won't get into any of that
stuff here, but after Calhoun's tenure
as vice president, he was elected to the
Senate. And in 1837, he gave a speech
called slavery as a positive good. And
in it, Calhoun rails against the
anti-slavery movements raging in the
north. And he takes aim at their
insistence that slavery be abolished
also in the south. And against such
efforts, Calhoun countered thusly.
First, because slavery and southern
society had been intimately intermingled
since the very birth of the south, to
abolish slavery would be to
simultaneously abolish the South. And
second, Calhoun argues that the
venerated slaveholders of the previous
generations who thought that slavery was
a necessary evil were wrong. In fact, he
argued slavery by all accounts is a
positive good. And he had his reasons
for making such a claim. Like not only
did slavery provide the South with its
very economic lifeblood, but he argued
it also benefited the enslaved people
themselves by raising these barbaric
Africans to a higher level of
civilization. And as strange as that
might sound to our modern ears, here's
where I tell you that Calhoun's
arguments were widely accepted in the
South because it seemed very plausible.
What I mean is Calhoun and those who
agreed with him framed the institution
of slavery in paternalistic terms. In
other words, slave owners were to be
exalted because they cared for their
enslaved people. like they fed them and
they clothed them, they taught them
Christian values and all the rest. And
that meant that slaveowning men and
women positively overflowed with charity
since by their reckoning, enslaved
people were not much different than
children who could not survive on their
own. And then further, Calhoun and his
crew compared that reality with the
brutal realities of wage labor in the
north. I mean, look at all those
industrial workers who were illreated
and making next to no money to support
themselves and living in nasty, squalid
conditions. And so with arguments like
that, many southerners began to believe
that slavery was actually the morally
superior form of labor compared to free
wage labor. And as a result, we can
witness during this period the
construction of a permanent wall of
separation between the white and black
people who lived in the south. And as
planters continued to migrate west to
find fresh land on which to plant their
kingdom of cotton, they brought this
positive good with them. And all this
taken together meant that the south had
fully developed a distinct regional
identity centered on white supremacy and
the perpetuation of slavery. And I hope
you can begin to see how this is going
to lead to a proper civil war in the
next period. I mean, when an institution
like slavery and ideas like white
supremacy are baked into the very DNA of
a society, and the leaders of that
society preach the goodness of those
things with evangelical fervor, well,
you know, compromise is simply not an
option. Well, okay, since you likely
have a test coming up, you can click
here to grab my A Push Heimler review
guide, or you can click here to watch my
other videos from unit 4. I'm glad you
came around, and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. I'm lar.